So before we get to the problem of ranking web
在探讨对网络搜索结果进行排名的问题之前
search results, I want to talk about one more interesting recursive
我想谈一个更有趣的递归定义
definition, the fibonacci series. And fibonacci numbers are one of
斐波纳契数列 (Fibonacci Series) 斐波纳契数是数学中
the most interesting things in mathematics. Once you know about them,
最有趣的事情之一 一旦你对它们有所了解
you'll see them all over the place, both in nature
你会在所有的地方看到它们 无论是在自然
and in human designs. The name comes from Leonardo da
还是在人类设计中 这个名字来源于Leonardo da Pisa
Pisa who was also know as fibonacci. And back in
他也被称为 Fibonacci 早在
1202 he published a book called Liber Abaci. The root Abaci
1202年 他出版了一本名为 Liber Abaci 的书 (书名为拉丁语)
is the same as the one for abacus the calculating
Abaci 与算盘 (abacus) 的词根相同 表示一种计算
machine. And this translates loosely as book of calculus. This
工具 书名被译为《计算之书》(Book of Calculus)
was the book that introduced Indian mathematics to the west.
本书将印度数学引入西方
In particular it introduced what we now know as Arabic
特别介绍了我们现在知道的阿拉伯
numerals. This replace the Roman numeral system that was then
数字 这取代了当时广泛使用的罗马
widely used. And part of what fibonacci did in the
数字体系 Fibonacci 在书中所做的一部分是
book was show, how much easier it is to do
展示 使用十进制
calculations, using numbers in the decimal systems where the place,
中的数字进行计算有多容易
where the number is indicates its value. And as part
其中的数字表示其值 书中部分内容
of the book introduce these problems, and showed how to
是介绍一些问题 并说明如何
solve them using calculation. The problem that became known as
使用计算解决这些问题 这个后来被称为
the fibonacci numbers was one of the problems in the book.
斐波纳契数列的问题 就是书中的问题之一
And he posed a problem like this. So at the
他提出的问题是这样的 一开始
beginning, we have one pair of rabbits, and it takes
我们有 1 对兔子 它需要
one month for a rabbit to produce offspring, and every
1 个月时间来生出后代 每个月
month a mature rabbit will produce a new pair of rabbits,
1 对成熟的兔子会生出 1 对新的兔子
so at month one, we had one pair of
因此在月份 1 我们有 1 对
rabbits. At month two, well, we have the one pair
兔子 在月份 2 我们有一开始
we started with. And now we have a new pair.
的那对兔子 而且现在我们有了 1 对新的
We have two pairs of rabbits. And now at month
我们有 2 对兔子 现在在月份 3
three the baby rabbits aren't yet ready to produce offspring.
兔宝宝还没有准备好来生产
It takes a month for the rabbits to reach maturity.
兔子需要 1 个月的时间来达到成熟期
But these two will produce new offspring each month. So
但是这 2 只每个月将产生新的后代 所以
we have one new pair of baby rabbits and the
我们又有 1 对新的兔宝宝 还有
rabbits that were born in month two, well they've had
在月份 2 出生的 2 只兔子 并且他们已经经历了
a month to get bigger. So now, they're mature rabbits.
一个月的成长期 所以现在 它们是成熟的兔子
So we had three pairs at the end of month
那么 我们在月份 3 结束时有 3 对兔子
three. So month four we still have the three pairs of
所以在月份 4 我们仍然拥有我们已有的
rabbits we had, rabbits never die in this model, and
3 对兔子 兔子在这个模型中不会死亡
the two pairs that are mature, both of those will now
这 2 对是成熟的 现在这 2 对会
produce new rabbits. So we have two new pairs of
生出新的兔子 因此 我们有 2 对新的
baby rabbits. The baby rabbits that were born in month three,
兔宝宝 这对出生在月份 3 的兔宝宝
well now those are mature. So now we have
现在都是成熟的 所以现在我们有
three pairs of mature rabbits, and two pairs of baby
3 对成熟兔和 2 对兔宝宝
rabbits, so we have five pairs of rabbits total. And
所以我们一共有 5 对兔子 然后
this keeps going, so the model assumed that rabbits never
继续这样下去 模型假设兔子不会死去
die, that every month each pair of mature rabbits
那么每个月每对成熟兔
produces a new pair of rabbit babies. And it takes
生出 1 对新的兔宝宝 每对兔子
one month for a pair of rabbits that spawn, to
从初生到成熟需要 1 个月的时间
become mature. So in month five, the three mature pairs
所以 在月份 5 这 3 对成熟兔
of rabbits, will all produce new offspring. New offspring,
都会生产新的后代、新的后代
new offspring, three new offspring. And the two that
新的后代 3 对新的后代 而且这 2 对
are a month old, that were born in month
有 1 个月大了 它们出生在月份 4
four, now become mature. So this isn't a very
现在变得成熟 所以 这不是一个很
accurate model of how rabbits reproduce. It's good for
精确的模型来表现兔子的繁衍 这对我们很好
us, if it was an accurate model, it would
如果它是一个精确的模型 那么
only take a few years for rabbits to control
只需要几年 兔子就会控制
the entire planet. But it's an interesting mathematical model.
整个地球 但是 这是一个有趣的数学模型
And the model that this poses, we can write in
而且这种模型的结构 我们可以以
a more formal way. So, the number of rabbits is
一个更正式的方式来书写 那么 兔子的数量是
the number of rabbits we had in the previous month,
我们上个月拥有的兔子数量
since those rabbits don't want to die. So in month five,
由于这些兔子不想死 所以在月份 5
we have the five pairs that we had in the
我们有 5 对上个月获得的
previous month, plus all of the rabbits that were mature, meaning,
兔子 加上所有的成熟兔 也就是
all of the rabbits that we had, two months ago,
我们 2 个月前拥有的兔子
which was three if we're on month five while those reproduce.
这个数量为 3 如果我们是在月份 5
So we have three new pairs of rabbits, plus
那么我们有 3 对新兔子 加上
the five that we have in the previous month. And
我们在上个月拥有的 5 然后
this keeps going. So we could in month six, we're
继续下去 那么我们在月份 6 了 我们
going to have the eight rabbits that we had at the
将有 8 对 我们在月份 5 结束时
end of month five, plus the five mature pairs,
拥有的兔子 再加上 5 对成熟兔
one, two, three, four, five, will each reproduce. So we'll
1、2、3、4、5 每对都将再生产 所以我们会
have five new pairs, and that will give us 13
有 5 对新的 这会给我们 13
pairs of rabbits. So this was the model fibonacci developed.
对兔子 那么 这就是斐波纳契模型
And the question is, can you figure out, at the end
然后问题是 你能否计算出 在
of month n, given any number n, how many rabbits will
月份 n 结束时 给定任意数 n 将会有多少只
there be? So the way we define this mathematically is a
兔子？我们在数学上定义这个的方式与
little different from the way, fibonacci posed the question. And that's
斐波纳契提出的问题 略有不同 这是
because in modern mathematics, we usually like our series to start
因为在现代数学中 我们通常喜欢使我们的数列
with a zero. If we are thinking of modeling rabbits, well
从 0 开始 如果我们考虑兔子模型 那么
that doesn't quite make sense to start with zero rabbits. But
从 0 只兔子开始没有什么意义
if we're thinking of it as a more general series, it does.
但是如果我们考虑它作为一种更通用的数列 它是需要的
So the way it's defined mathematically is that
因此它在数学上定义的方式是
we say that the fibonacci number zero, is defined
我们说 fibonacci(0) 被定义为 0
as zero. Fibonacci number one is defined as one,
fibonacci(1) 被定义为 1
and those are our two base cases. So this
这些就是我们的两个基本情况 所以这
is different from the other recursive definitions we've seen
与我们见过的其他递归定义不同
in that the two base cases. Previously, all of
它有 2 个基本情况 之前我们的所有
our definitions just had one base case. And then
定义都只有一个基本情况 那么接下来
we can define every other fibonacci number, but first
我们可以定义每个其他数字的斐波纳契数 但首先
we'll be starting from these base cases. And so, the fibonacci number n,
我们会从这些基本情况开始 所以 fibonacci(n)
where n is some whole number greater than one, is, well we
其中 n 为比 1 大的整数 是我们
have all the rabbits in the previous month. So, that's fibonacci of n minus 1,
前一个月拥有的所有兔子 这个 fibonacci(n-1)
plus, all the new babies. And the number of new
加上所有的新宝宝 而新宝宝的数量
babies is the number of rabbits we had two months
是 2 个月之前我们拥有的兔子数量
ago, those are all the mature rabbits. That gets added
这些都是成熟的兔子 这被加到
to the number of rabbits we had the previous month.
我们上个月拥有的兔子数量上
So that's how we define fibonacci numbers. This defines every fibonacci number
所以这就是我们如何定义斐波纳契数 这定义了每个斐波纳契数
in terms of the two base cases, and in the one recursive case.
用 2 个基本情况和 1 个递归情况
So, your goal is to define a procedure called fibonacci.
所以 你的目标是定义一个名为 fibonacci 的过程
That takes a natural number as input. So, numbers starting
这需要一个自然数作为输入 所以 数字
from 0, any whole number 0 or higher, and outputs
从 0 开始 以及所有比 0 大的整数 然后输出
the value of that fibonacci number, defined using this recursive definition.
该数字的斐波那契数 使用这个递归定义来定义